<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Guy de Maupassant</title>
            <author>Blanche Roosevelt</author>
            <editor>Oscar Wilde</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>Digital Edition, transcribed and annotated</edition>
            <respStmt><resp>Project manager</resp><name>Elizabeth Shand</name></respStmt>
            <respStmt><resp>New annotations by</resp><name>Michelle Robinson</name></respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>The Woman's World</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace></pubPlace>
                     <publisher></publisher>
                     <date when="1899-01-10">1 October 1899</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
         <head>Guy de Maupassant</head>
            <p>Seven years ago a story was published called “Boule de Suif,” and, although it bore the signature of an unknown writer, created a sensation in the Parisian corps of authors. This august galaxy immediately recognised in the new aspirant for literary honours a mind of extraordinary power, and a pen of no less extraordinary ability. "<foreign xml:lang="fr">Boule de Suif</foreign>" was followed by a book of poems, and in rapid succession appeared "<foreign xml:lang="fr">La Maison Tellier</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Mlle. Fifi</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Une Vie</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Les Contes de la Bécasse</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Au Soleil</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Les Soeurs Rondoli</foreign>,” “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Bel Ami</foreign>,” and “<foreign xml:lang="fr">La Petite Roque</foreign>.” Each succeeding work not only gave the public the highest opinion of <name>M. de Maupassant</name>’s natural talent, but demonstrated his perfect mastership in the art of literary composition. His name was mentioned with those mysterious accents which promise a future, and the Parisians discovered that the French world of letters was richer by a genius whose star had dawned with singular power and brightness. <name>Guy de Maupassant</name> soon became the theme in public and private circles, in high life and low, in artistic and Bohemian gatherings; his talent was discussed and his personality questioned. Who he was, whether noble or plebeian; what he looked like, and where he came from; if young or old, rich or poor; and was “De Maupassant” a real name or an incognito? No one could answer these questions, but after the electric success of "<foreign xml:lang="fr">Bel Ami</foreign>” everybody seemed to be acquainted with the noble author. He dined with the <name>Princess Mathilde</name> at her very select parties, he was constantly seen at the <name>Baroness de Poilly</name>’s most distinguished “at-homes,” and noted patrons of art in patrician and literary circles vied with each other in rendering homage to his name and ability. While the public fully recognised <name>M. de Maupassant</name>’s powers, critics in general were divided as to his particular kind of talent. All agreed, however, that he was not only strikingly original, but an apt disciple in the style of the greatest French writers. He was compared with <name>Stendhal</name>, <name>Zola</name>, and many other celebrities, but the truest judges soon discovered that the author of “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Bel Ami</foreign>” and “<foreign xml:lang="fr">Une Vie</foreign>” more especially resembled one other whose perfection was then universally acknowledged—the author of “Mme. Bovary” and “Salammbo;” in fact, in <name>M. de Maupassant</name>’s earlier efforts the master is as readily traced through the pupil’s performance as in the great works of <name>Raphael</name> we feel the force of Perugini’s art. On the appearance of <name>M. Maxime Duchamp</name>’s life of <name>Flaubert</name>, a spirited journalistic controversy revealed the fact that not alone was <name>De Maupassant</name> a disciple of the Rouen writer, but was his pupil, friend, and the loyal defender of a calumniated man. <name></name>Guy de Maupassant’s nature spoke clearly in this defence of one gone before, and his fidelity as a pupil is shown by conscientiously following in the master’s footsteps.</p>
               <p>Like Flaubert, no pains are too great to take; the same attention is paid to the word as to the phrase, to the leading article as to the romance. It is always interesting to notice the working methods of successful men, and that of De Maupassant is another proof that what is worth doing is worth doing well. He never writes a story until the plot, characters, and situations have thoroughly ripened in his mind. It took him three years to sketch out “Boule de Suif,” his first, and by many considered to be his best, work; he studied seven years with Flaubert before he dared publish the simplest study. This artist used to say to him, “Take any object in nature—a flower, a brook, a bird—look at it, and then describe it, not as I see it, but as you intend me to see it.”</p>
               <p>“Occasionally,” says De Maupassant, “I hit it off at once, but oftener I had to describe a thing twenty times before Flaubert considered it well done; I had to try over and over and over again before I could please the friend or satisfy the inexorable critic.”</p>
               <p>In consequence of this rigorous apprenticeship, M. de Maupassant has earned the right to be called a stylist. His long and laborious application to the trade—the mechanical part of authorship—has been such that, no matter what he undertakes, the most ungenerous of critics can find fault with neither style, language, nor expression. De Maupassant modestly says of himself, yet with a certain truth, “I am not a man of talent, but a skilled workman;” and, to quote a paragraph from the preface to “Pierre and Jean,” he aptly remarks: “Whatever the thing one wishes to say, there is but one word to express that thing, one verb to animate it, and one adjective to qualify it. It is, then, necessary to hunt till one has discovered that word, that verb, and that adjective, and never be content with getting near or around or about it; and, above all, never have recourse to even the happiest artifices or tricks of language to avoid the difficulty of precise word-expression.”</p>
               <p>De Maupassant is singularly free from hyperbole, metaphor, and circumlocution; he is also devoid of humour, in the witty sense of the word; but no one surpasses him in the force of ironic shrewdness, or in scenes depicting merciless sarcasm. “Bel Ami,” “Boule de Suif,” and “Yvette” particularly, abound in these effects. Being a stylist, he is often obliged to impoverish the action in order to preserve the correctness of classic utterance. He is at present too young to fully emancipate himself from this artistic obligation. He sometimes errs in coldness and stilted language, but with time will have acquired such a fluency of diction that no conventionality can hamper his muse.</p>
               <p>To be strictly critical, as a romance-writer De Maupassant is deficient in constructive power; he rarely or never describes love-scenes with tenderness or even the ordinary sentiment, and his pathos is the strong rebutting conclusion bound to follow upon situations the result of forcible objective reasoning. This is particularly noticeable in “Une Vie,” which is masterful in the beginning and ends feebly; also in “Pierre et Jean,” perhaps the most complete of his complete studies; but his sketches of character, description of the French bourgeois and peasant as they really exist, are unrivalled for keen analysis, truthful incident, and local colouring.</p>
               <p>When M. de Maupassant chose the most difficult of literary methods—to wit, objective presentation—he sank his personality and realised that, unless a most accomplished workman, his own pen would be the first to betray his mind. Most novelists who can write can suppose characters and run the gamut of imaginary sentiments. This subjective argument, which brings a “Maud” or “Mary” or “Charles” into the world, and, always by giving the author’s ideas, raises, educates, marries, murders, or hangs them at will, is a very common affair; but the great art in the writer is to be impersonal, to make the story tell itself by its active situations, to make inanimate objects move and dumb things talk; in short, to bring the whole artillery of Nature’s forces to bear upon the scene, and show what may be gained by the triple alliance of Nature, of art, and of artifice or mechanical perfection in workmanship. M. de Maupassant’s books do not appeal to the general Anglo-Saxon public. The eternal theme immortalized by Molière—the deceived husband, the faithless wife, and the triumphant lover—present most striking individual characters, but painted in their native blackness, and with a pessimistic view of life in general, they shock the reader accustomed to ethical tales, and the belief that perhaps the world holds one noble soul. M. de Maupassant’s mental resources and habitual method of depicting only the dark side of existence are fairly betrayed in the following from the preface to his latest novel, “Pierre et Jean”: —</p>
               <p>“The realist, if he be an artist, will seek above all things, not alone to give us the ordinary photograph of life, but also to give us a more complete, striking, and penetrating vision than life or reality itself. .. More than this, life is composed of the most varied kinds of things—the most unexpected, the most contrary, and the most mis-mated; life is brutal, without sequence, without connection, full of inexplicable catastrophes, of illogical and contradictory events,  which must come under the head of—things in general … Great artists are simply those who impose upon humanity their own particular illusion.”</p>
               <p>“Bel Ami,” M. de Maupassant’s most sustained and brilliant effort, is also, strange to say, the author’s favourite work. Bel Ami is a being who, at the outset, represents a character absolutely denuded of one redeeming trait. He begins life a renegade soldier, through force of circumstances becomes a journalist, and, through impudence, a man of position. The other characters in the book are on a par with this loathsome but masterful creation. I once said to Maupassant, “Is it possible there are such people living in the world, and is there a second Bel Ami on earth?” He laughed and answered, “There is not only a second, but a first, Bel Ami in person. He is a study from life, but I did not tell a quarter of what I knew about him. The fact is, truths seemed so monstrous when put on paper that they lost all their probability. I was obliged to modify them; firstly, they appeared unnatural; and, secondly, so violent in contrast with fiction in a work of fiction that they were absolutely inartistic.”</p>
               <p>It will readily be seen that M. de Maupassant does not furnish sentiment for the crowd, neither does he sacrifice himself and gratify the vanity of the crowd by a bid for popular favour. “Pierre et Jean” is dark, cruel, terrible, and repellant; but it is real. As a work of art, it is above the heads of the masses; but as a picture of suffering and agonized human nature, it cannot fail in appealing to every human being, cannot be read without bringing tears to the eyes of the most insensible.</p>
               <p>Guy de Maupassant is a Norman of ancient lineage, and was born August 5th, 1850, in the Château de Miromesnil, near Dieppe. History tells us that his paternal ancestor was ennobled by Louis XIV., made a marquis, and given various other titles of distinction, with the fiefs of Maupassant and Valmont.</p>
               <p>At an early age Guy was sent to the ecclesiastical College of Yvetôt in Normandy, whence, having shocked the pious fathers by having written some improper verses, he was immediately and permanently expelled. From Yvetôt the young poet was sent to complete his studies at the Lycée de Rouen, the well-known academy in the Maid of Orleans’ city. At the end of his curriculum he departed with high honours, and proceeded to Paris, where he was employed for upwards of six years at the Ministry of the Marine. De Maupassant once wrote to me, “I came to Paris after the war, and saw a great deal of Flaubert, then residing in the grand metropolis. He always received me with sincere kindness and friendship, and, confiding to him that I thought of a literary career, he made me study my profession and learn the secrets of style absolutely as workmen study who learn any trade whatsoever. I labored in this way, following his counsels, for seven long years, but not daring to publish anything until he had given me positive permission. At last, in 1880, I ventured with ‘Boule de Suif’ and, a month later, a little volume of poems. After these came ‘Bel Ami,’ ‘Mlle. Fifi,’ &c.; &c.;”</p>
               <p>M. de Maupassant lives in Paris with his cousin, De Poitevin, a fine landscape-painter, at No. 10, Rue Mont-chanin, Quartier Malesherbes. His house is charming, luxurious, and artistic. While the exterior is very simple, the interior is a wilderness of Genoese tapestries, Louis XV. furniture, sculpted cabinets, and rare porcelain. In the drawing-room are an admirable head of Flaubert, some charming Normandy studies by M. de Poitevin, well-lined book-shelves, and an immense bear-skin, which stretches its white length over the entire parquet. Beyond are the poet’s bed-chamber, a splendid but somberly furnished apartment, and, further on, a sort of writing-room and conservatory in one—a perfect museum of rare and interesting objects; amongst others, the author’s MSS., piles of autograph letters from some of the greatest living and dead celebrities, and a magnificent statue of Buddha, representing the high priest of this religion with so benign an aspect that, were the original at all like the effigy, none could resist being a follower of this teacher and faith. Our author’s favourite home is Étretat, the well-known sea-side resort in Normandy.</p>
               <p>In personal appearance Guy de Maupassant is of medium height, solid, well-built, and has the bearing of a soldier; he has a fine characteristic Norman head, with the straight line from neck to crane which we see in the medallions of the old Conquest warriors; his forehead is low, rather too heavily lined; and his hair, brown and wavy, is now combed straight back in the fashion of the modern Roman youth. In short, M. de Maupassant has such a look of cheeriness that he reminds one of a clear autumn day—an agreeable harmony in russet colours and russet tints: dark brown laughing eyes, a shapely mouth, half concealed by a heavy brown mustache, an olive skin mantled with red and a general healthy ruddiness, give this character and warmth to his physiognomy. In France they call him a “très joli garcon,” and I presume he might pass for that anywhere. With all that, one is most pleased with the expression of his countenance, which indicates simplicity, intelligence, and great good-nature. Dress this gentleman in a tweed suit—do not start!—also of russet tints, and you will see him as he stands on the balcony of La Guillette, or as I saw him one summer day at the gate, waiting for a friend who was coming down the road to his cottage. “La Guillette,” the name “Guy” feminised, is a pretty place, and the author has made of it a delightful residence. Here he spends several months in each year, and here he has written the greater number of his books.</p>
               <p>De Maupassant loves France, but he adores the tropics. His visit to Africa has resulted in some exquisite studies; amongst others, “Marocca” and “Au Soleil,” two admirable and delightful works. He says that the African is the only climate which suits him, and ever since his return keeps up the souvenir by living in an atmosphere that would stifle any but himself. The hottest day in the summer is never too hot for him, and the temperature in his study would be considered high in the baths of Hamam.
              <p> M. de Maupassant has travelled widely, but never visited England till the summer of 1886. He was invited specially as the guest of Baron Ferdinand de Rothschild, and it was at the magnificent seat of Wadesden that he was introduced to the charm of English country life. His cultured host had made up an unusually distinguished party to meet him, and, according to the French author, this visit was “one of the most interesting events of his life.” After the stay in Hampshire he returned to town, and, to the general surprise, said he would not “do” London, but desired to go the next morning to Oxford. “My friend Paul Bourget” (the gifted young poet and novelist), he said, “writes me: ‘You must see Oxford, the only genuine mediaeval town in the world; it will charm you. Don’t fail to see it.’” The following day we took an early train thither, and, although in August, the air was raw, the wind high, and weather atrocious. Before we arrived an accident delayed the train, a terrific storm arose, and we reached the mediaeval town in anything but a cheerful humour. De Maupassant was shivering from cold, and, to quote his own words, “fainting from hunger.” “I am fond of antiquities,” he observed, “but first of all breakfast! breakfast! breakfast!” This meal was admirable and prolonged. In the meanwhile the rain fell with torrential fury, and the entire town seemed one vast wreckage of Nature. In spite of the discouraging aspect without, our author cried, “Ah, now for some sight-seeing I promised Bourget, etcetera!”</p>
               <p>A guide informed us that, although the colleges were closed, neither wind, weather, nor circumstance could alter the beauty of this mediaeval town. Our selection of a cab was unfortunate; the driver was intoxicated and the vehicle shattered. But we drove boldly forward. De Maupassant, with his back to the horses, was trembling and regretting Africa, when he was startled by a terrific rap at the window. The carriage stopped, and the driver, dripping, gravely opened the door. Shaking his head with one maudlin and unparalleled human gesture, he hiccoughed, “This—is—the Shel—donian!” M. de Maupassant did not understand English, but the accents threw him into fits, and I thought the rest of our party would simply go into convulsions. The classic Jehu, although not understanding the cause of our mirth, smiled responsively, waived ceremony, and began the stereotyped history of the institute.</p>
               <p>At other stopping-places other histories were repeated in a similar manner. Finally between laughing and choking, De Maupassant got into such a state that I feared we should be arrested for lunatics, and proposed returning to town. At the station a facetious telegram was despatched on the spot to M. Paul Bourget, and we swung into the train just as the guard was closing the doors.
               <p>Arrived at the London terminus, we informed M. de Maupassant that, having “done” Oxford, one great historical place yet remained to be visited. He was carried without demur to Madame Tussaud’s. After finishing the afternoon in the Chamber of Horrors, the day was concluded by a dinner and a visit to the Savoy Theatre. Although aware of M. de Maupassant’s antipathy to singing drama, we felt that, in justice to England, he must hear a genuine English operetta. At its close he professed himself really charmed. The next morning I received the following: —“I am too cold; this city is too cold; I am leaving for Paris. Au revoir! many thanks, &c.—De Maupassant.”</p>
               <p>And this is the way one French author saw England! I gave a celebrated poet a description of how he at least saw Oxford. “Was it not comic?” I added.
              <p> “Comic!” he cried; “I think it was most tragic.”
                 <p><name="author">Blanche Roosevelt.</name></p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
