<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Shopping in London</title>
            <author>A.E.F. Eliot James</author>
            <editor>Oscar Wilde</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>Digital Edition, transcribed and annotated</edition>
            <respStmt><resp>New annotations by</resp><name>Elizabeth Shand</name></respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>The Woman's World</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace></pubPlace>
                     <publisher></publisher>
                     <date when="1899-01-10">1 October 1899</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Shopping in London possesses an indescribable fascination for the ordinary woman, whether she be a fair mondain who, rich in this world’s wealth, spends her mornings in the season driving from this well-known shop to that, acquiring a vast amount of fashionable frippery for the adornment of her house and her person; or the country cousin, who arrives in town when Society (with a large S, please) has departed, and is burdened with countless impossible commissions from her hosts of friends and relations; or the regular sale frequenter, who goes the round of the London houses, at the half-yearly sales to some purpose.</p>
          <p>Walk down Regent Street on a June morning, and mark the smart carriages waiting for their respective owners, who are enjoying themselves in thoroughly feminine fashion, inspecting the latest Paris importations; the newest creations in hats and bonnets at Louise’s; the freshest models in mantles from Worth, Felix, and Pingat at Jay’s; the most cloudy and diaphanous of ball toilettes at Howell and James’s, Lewis and Allenby’s, Swan and Edgar’s; the last of Liberty’s art fabrics and harmoniously-coloured tea-gowns. Take a turn down Conduit Street, and see how full are Redfern’s show-rooms. Try New Bond Street, Oxford Street, or any of the streets containing well-known fashionable shops, and note the people thronging them. Yes; it is a favorite, if an expensive amusement, this of shopping in London, and one very freely indulged in at all seasons by different classes: the shopkeepers, who gauge with great accuracy public taste, knowing exactly how to cater for their various customers.</p>
            <p>There are several distinct types of the genus shopper – shoppers of both sexes, clever and weak, extravagant and thrifty; those who know their own minds and those who do not; those who submit to be led by the shopman or shopwoman, whose torrent of specious argument they are wholly incapable of resisting; those, on the contrary, who heed not the voice of the country-skipper, charm be never so insinuatingly, but sternly combat any manifested desire to lead them from their original purpose – who, entering a shop with their minds fully made up as to the exact article they require, buy that, and that only, if they can find it; if not, go in quest of the same elsewhere, refusing to be cajoled into purchasing six-buttoned gloves for the ordinary price of those with two, because “they are only sold at that low price, being bankrupt stock;” waving also on one side the remnant of ribbon and silk handkerchief, those baits held out to the unwary. In striking contrast to these downright, stick-to-their-purpose people, are those who buy simply because the thing offered “is really so absurdly cheap,” not that they are in the least in want of it. Such people are good rubbish accumulators, excellent clients of the dustmen. A case in point is that of an old Frenchman, who bought an immense number of yards of hideous yellow tarlatan only because the piece was offered to him for a mere song. His daughters, unfortunate young women, were doomed to appear “in yellow, all in yellow,” at the festivities in their neighbourhood that and succeeding winters, as also their lady friends, to whom their father generously presented yellow gowns, until “M. Dieudonne’s livery” became a standing joke against the wearers of the cheap tarlatan.</p>
            <p>Shopping in London in the sale season is made a complete science of by the clever type of shopper, who knows exactly what houses to visit for the best bargains; where to get cheap dress materials, and ready-made but well finished-off costume; good lingerie and household linen. Whiteley’s and Chapman’s are well-known haunts of this variety of shopper, who, for a very moderate outlay, will replenish her own and her daughters’ wardrobes, not forgetting the linen closet. She is rarely taken in, knowing that really good firms, who have their name to keep up, must sell off old stock reasonably before restocking with fresh goods, and who, charging high prices early in the season to regular customers, can afford to sell at bona fide reduced rates at their half-yearly sales. </p>
            <p>Liberty’s is the chosen resort of the artistic shopper. Note this lady robed in “Liberty silk” of sad-coloured green, with rather more than a suspicion of yellow in ribbons, sash, and hat (suggestive of a badly-made salad) who talks learnedly to her young friend – clothed in russet-brown, with salmon-pink reliefs showing in quaint slashings in unexpected places – of “the value of tone,” of negatives and positives, of delicious half-tones, and charming introductions of colour, fingering the while the art stuffs and fade silks shown her with a certain amount of reverence expressive of the artistic yearnings of her soul. We may be tolerably certain that such an one has her drawing-room arranged in the very last scheme of colour – cool silver-grey, possibly, in conjunction with yellow terra-cotta and ivory, or the new red-brown with the faintest, palest of olive-greens; the floor in the parqueterie, with rich Eastern rugs laid down on it, furniture in dark wood, Moorish style; three-legged tiny tables, yellow, white, or pale green; graceful palms in huge pots of Eastern pottery, in beaten iron stands; a fretwork arch in wood dividing the double rooms. Imagination further conjures up the lady herself in a tea-gown of silver-grey pongee cashmere, with full front of yellow Surah; but when we find ourselves considering that terra-cotta and ivory silk would best suit her colouring and individuality, we mentally pull ourselves together, becoming conscious that we are staring somewhat fixedly at the Artistic One. So we leave her, deep in a discussion with her friend and the Eastern-garmented shopgirl as to the relative merits of a sage-green or dull red serge portiere, and pursue our character studies elsewhere.</p>
            <p>A buxom dame, who has “country” writ all over her in legible letters, has brought her well-developed daughter (we had inwardly christened her Mary Jane before her mother’s loud-voiced appeal confirmed us in our conjecture as to her Christian name) up for a visit to town. They are about to enter Redfern’s. Mamma has seen the Ladies Greytowers in neat tailor-made gowns when they have honoured with their presence the bazaars and flower-shows in their own neighbourhood, and, while admiring the fit of the said gowns, has thought them a trifle plainer than she should like her girls to wear, being, of course, unable to appreciate the chicdom (to coin a word) of the costumes. Hearing indirectly where they were made, she has decided that, on her yearly shopping expedition to London, she will buy a tailor-built gown for Maryjane (she runs both names together) and one of Lady G.’s bonnets for herself. After rejecting several pretty, simple gowns in fawn, grey, and green, which would have toned the girl down – albeit it would have been, as they say in Cornwall, “cream on pilchards” – she fixes on a dull red, rather lavishly embroidered in red and gold. Alterations are required, the redundant lines of “Maryjane’s” figure not being exactly those on which the model is built. Let that pass. We mildly wonder on what occasion daughter and mother will elect to astonish their neighbours, for we intuitively feel that mamma will invest in something, if possible, as unsuitable to her as is the selection she has made for her daughter to that damsel. Wonder is changed to horror when the couple pause agape before a bonnet-shop, and the mother, gazing at a poppy hat, exclaims, “The exact thing, Maryjane, to match your new dress!” Neither of them carries colours in the eye; this is evident, for bonnet and gown together will be simply agonising. Even the saleswoman – who has a sense of the external fitness of things, though blissfully unconscious of the prior purchase – suggests a pretty, black lace-covered hat, with gracefully upturned brim, and bramble-blossoms nestling amid the lace, knowing it will soften down and so increase the rustic milkmaid sort of beauty the girl possesses, for Mary Jane is, to a certain extent, comely. But no; poppy hat, vivid scarlet, is bought and paid for triumphantly. As the vision of that hat, with that gown, presents itself to our mental vision, we shudder, and resolutely change the current of our thoughts. Mother consults note-book for address of aristocratic milliner, and, energetically hailing a four-wheeler (for she is never quite sure of her localities in the metropolis), hies her off to make her purchase. She hopes, yet fears, to be served by the head of the establishment, and “How shall I address her?” is a quick question which causes her great mental perturbation, making the worthy woman work frantically in sheer nervousness at the obstinate first button of her right-hand glove until glove and button part company, and the state of that glove is now incomparably worse than it was before; but this troubles her little, it is a mere detail. Shall she say “your Grace”? No; that she happily remembers is for a duchess. Shall she call her “my lady, or “Lady G.”? “Your ladyship” finally wins the day. Destination reached, she “your ladyship’s” the forewoman, who has her risible muscles under perfect control, to her heart’s content. “Maryjane,” a quiet spectator of the scene, and being, rare thing in these days, a firm believer in the wisdom of her parent, thinks how well mother is doing it. A remarkably pretty bonnet is under discussion, an airy creation of black Chantilly, dandelions and downy seed-vessels. Something more showy would be to the buyer’s taste, but here she allows herself to be led, especially when she is told “We sold one almost exactly like that to the Countess of X. a few days since,” for the clever forewoman has risen to the occasion, and now thoroughly understands the customer. Lady G., who is paying a flying out-of-season visit to town to look after the welfare of her boutique, here enters, and the forewoman appeals to the higher authority as to whether the bonnet “does not suit madame a merreille.” Consternation of buyer, who feels intensely small inwardly, but wisely refrains from saying any of the pretty speeches she had previously rehearsed, pays rather a long figure for her bonnet, and departs, consoled by her daughter’s “Never mind, mother, no one will hear of your mistake, and she” (meaning the aristocratic shopowner) “said it suited you well. It’s a love of a bonnet, I never saw you look better than you do in it, and it’s just like the Countess of X.’s, you know.”</p>
            <p>Some shoppers there are, these from the country too, who insist on carrying their own purchases home. Such are generally burdened with other people’s commissions, which they undertake willingly, no matter what remote corners of London they have to visit to carry them out, for do they not love shopping and bringing home the spoils? No matter how many the parcels, how large, or how bulky and awkward to handle, they stagger along under them. If there is one sight more calculated than another woman on a warm day to make one feel thoroughly uncomfortable, it is that of the parcel-embarrassed woman. Here is an example. Elderly stout female (inveterate parcel-carriers are invariably stout) heavily laden with packages of all sizes and shapes, large and small, round, flat, and long. We feel with two street-boys, who have followed her evidently in the hopes of spoil, that a cab must be necessary. One boy, in mere sportiveness, hails a hansom and runs away. Parcel-bearer gesticulates wildly, and waves away from the cabman with her umbrella; in so doing drops a parcel tucked under her arm, but promptly sets her foot on it. Query: Is this action the result of former experiences in parcel-snatching? We pick it up, and, emboldened by having shown such a small favour, suggest a cab. But no; thanking us, she walks calmly down a whole cab-rank, braving the string of inquiries from the men. She is in search of a ‘bus, and struggles into one, parcels and all, regardless of the cross looks of the occupants, for there is only room for one fare of ordinary size, unparcelled. She is lost to our gaze, for which we are thankful.</p>
            <p>A final type of shopper – the bargainer, who fingers everything and audibly appraises it, asking the invariable question, “Is this reduced?” – insists on having huge bales unrolled, that she may see if they are more soiled inside than outside appearances indicates; – rubs calicoes so hard to see how much “dress” they have in them, that she soils the bit on which she operates – driving the unfortunate server nearly mad by turning goods over and asking for things he has not in stock – and then goes off, without having made a single purchase, holding out a promise of a future visit. 	A. E. F. Eliot-James.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
